אוקיי בוקר טוב *Okay boker tov*. Alright, today's דף Daf *daf* is
כ"ו *chof vav* and we pick up with the משנה Mishnah *mishnah*.
Alright, and the let's take a look. We dealt with writing גט
Get *get* לשמה lishma *lishmah* and the משנה Mishnah *mishnah* clearly seemed
to be all רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* because right, it
was about writing it for the name of the right man and
of the right woman and לשם גירושין *leshem gerushin*, so it was
all emphasized the writing and not the signing and that משנה Mishnah.
*mishnah* was a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* משנה Mishnah, *mishnah*
that focused on לשמה lishma *lishmah* and with that we're going to
continue with this next משנה Mishnah *mishnah*. So let's take a look.
הכותב טופסי גיטין Hakosev tofsay gittin. *Hakotev tofsei gittin*, people that are
writing the גט Get *get* form, meaning, you know, the boiler plate
part, you want to have it ready to be used at when
somebody comes for a גט Get *get*, you just take one of
them, you know, the pre-made ones, like now when you're getting married
you get a כתובה ketubah. *kesuvah*, you get one with the fill
in the blanks, so you want to have them ready to take.
So you're going ahead and you're writing the boiler plate part of
the גט Get *get*. צריך שיניח מקום האיש ומקום האישה ומקום הזמן
umakom hazman. *Tzarich she'yaniach mekom ha'ish umekom ha'ishah umekom hazman*. You have
to leave the critical information pieces blank. You know, you have to
leave blank the name of the place for the man's name, the
woman's name, and for the time. Now this is not saying that
it's לשמה lishma. *lishmah* although the previous משנה Mishnah *mishnah* was clearly
about לשמה lishma, *lishmah*, one could imagine that the reason you leave
these things blank is because you don't know those specifics. So of
course you're going to leave them blank. But of course the problem
is, well, then it would be like so obvious, then it would
be obvious. Of course, if you fill in with the wrong information,
you can't use it.
So we will see what this is about. Is it because you
just really don't have those specifics yet or is this a לשמה
lishma, *lishmah* issue? שטרי מלווה *Shtarei milveh*, now how about a writ
that's used to testify to the fact that somebody borrowed money,
and it's a what's that called? There's got to be a name
for that, a promissory note or something. And
now there there's obviously no לשמה lishma. *lishmah* requirement.
This is not the IOU itself, this is a document that testifies
to the fact that there was a
Well, it is the IOU, I mean there was not necessarily an
IOU written by the person who borrowed. It was that ראובן Reuven
*Reuven* borrowed from שמעון Shimon *Shimon* a hundred dollars and witnesses signed.
Right, exactly. So צריך שיניח מקום המלווה ומקום הלווה ומקום הממון ומקום
הזמן *tzarich she'yaniach mekom hamilveh umekom haloveh mekom hamamon umekom hazman*, the
space for the
lender, the debtor,
the amount of money,
and the date in which the money was borrowed. שטרי מקח *Shtarei
mekach*, if you're, you know, a document that's used for selling a
plot of land and you want to write the boiler plate part,
so that's fine, but צריך שיניח מקום הלוקח ומקום המוכר *tzarich she'yaniach
mekom halokeach umekom hamocher*, you have to leave blank the space for
writing the name of the buyer and of the seller. מקום הממון
*Mekom hamamon*, the amount of money, מקום השדה *mekom hasadeh*, the actual
location of the field that was purchased,
and מקום הזמן makom hazman. *mekom hazman*, and the date. מפני התקנה
*Mifnei hatakanah*, all of this is because of the תקנה takkana. *takanah*.
So what תקנה takkana? *takanah* is it? Okay, and obviously as I
said, to some degrees isn't all like self-evident, of course you can't
fill those blanks, you don't know that information yet. So רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says well we could imagine a scenario where you're anticipating it
happening, where you're hearing this husband and wife and they've been fighting
for like months and months and you say oh that's gone for
divorce, I might as well fill it out, or you know that
somebody's been really working on a deal to buy a plot of
land, so you figure might as well just pre-write this. Sort of
reminds me of the fact that you know all these newspapers, they
have obituaries written like years before the person dies, you know any
big public figure, yeah, you know any public figure, he's gonna die
eventually, so they basically have a pre-written obituary, if something new happens
they update it every few years, and then when the person actually
dies, it's ready to go. So you feel that the couple's ready
to get divorced or somebody ready to borrow money, you just go
ahead and you rewrite it, and you write it ahead of time.
So if there isn't a לשמה lishma? *lishmah* issue which there might
be by גט Get. *get*, it's not clear what the problem is
with these other things. So we will see about that in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, okay? So let's take a look, one minute, let's
finish the משנה Mishnah *mishnah*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda פוסל בכולן posel
bechulan *Rabbi Yehuda poseil bekullan*, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* says
nope, none of this is good, presumably he does not allow you
to write even the boiler plate part of it, and we'll see
presumably because he's afraid you'll come to do the essential part as
well. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, מכשיר בכולן machshir bekullan, *Rabbi Eliezer machshir
bekullan*, they're all okay, חוץ מגיטי נשים שנאמר shene'emar, בכתב לו
לשמה lishma *chutz migittei nashim shenee'mar bekosav lo lishmah*,
except for גט Get, *get* which has a לשמה lishma *lishmah* requirement
and here it's specifically associated with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*,
which raises the question of what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna
Kamma*'s position is, it also raises the question what is he saying,
is he saying that you can't even write the boiler plate by
a גט Get *get* because of the בכתב לו לשמה lishma? *bekosav
lo lishmah*, but the boiler plate isn't a problem? So the way
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*'s going to understand it is no, but because
it's so essential that it be לשמה lishma. *lishmah*... We don't even
let you write the boilerplate because if we let you do that,
you'll accidentally come to write the essential part as well. So it's
a type of גזירה. gezeira. By a גט Get we do not
allow even the boilerplate לשמה lishma because of... even the boilerplate because
the לשמה lishma requirement is so great that we have to make
that safeguard. Now, if that's true when it says מכשיר בכולן, machshir
bekullan he says everything else is okay. Is he adding anything new?
Oh, but all this other stuff you can write the boilerplate. Okay,
big deal, we sort of knew that. I mean, maybe יהודה Yehuda
maybe disagreed with that. So that's what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י Rashi,
says he's not מחדש mechadesh anything about the rest, you let you
write the boilerplate for the rest, not the תורף, toref, not the
essential part. But by a גט Get he doesn't even let you
write the boilerplate. תוספות Tosafot disagrees, and we're actually going to go
with תוספות's Tosafot read because it's a much better read of the
גמרא Gemara, later. And תוספות Tosafot says that Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer is
being extra strict by גט Get and not letting you write the
boilerplate, but he's being extra lenient by the other stuff. And that
מכשיר בכולן machshir bechulan means, no, anything that's not, meaning his basic
point is, look guys, it's all about לשמה. lishma So anything that's
not about לשמה, lishma right, like you can go ahead and write
the whole thing. It's now, you can't write ראובן Reuven borrowed שמעון
Shimon a hundred dollars and sign the witnesses yet. You don't put
on the witnesses until the money is lent. You don't write somebody
sold his plot of land and you sell, write, put on the
witnesses until it's actually sold. But you're the סופר sofer and you
know this guy is telling you, "I'm working on a deal, I...
get that שטר shtar ready for me, prepare the document, here are
the specifics." So why not go ahead and write it? And you'll
have the witnesses sign when it actually, the deal goes through. So
the way that תוספות Tosafot reads Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer is a stronger
read of him both in the משנה mishna and in the גמרא,
Gemara is that he says you, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma made
everything the same, write the boilerplate, don't write the essentials. Rabbi יהודה
Yehuda said none of it is good, you cannot even write the
boilerplate, he's super strict. Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer says look, for a גט
get, I'm going to be super strict and say don't even write
the boilerplate because it's a very, you know, you've got to be
לשמה, lishma so you don't want to be fooling around there. But
for everything else, גזונטהייט, gezunteheit, write the whole thing and it's not
a problem, you'll sign the witnesses when it comes time to finalize
the sale. Okay, so he's totally lenient by everything else and totally
strict by גט. get, You had a question starting, yeah?
So the Rabbi יהודה's Yehuda position that everything, that you can't write
anything, if you take that interpretation, that would invalidate every loan made
for the last
150-200 years.
Yeah, so everyone uses a pre-paid, a pre-printed, right, exactly. Yeah, so
we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara it's good we don't פוסק pasken
like that. Yes.
I just wanted to ask about the concept of לשמה. lishma, Is
it not that once I write the specific name of this woman
and this man, just the act of writing that specifically, that's not
enough to constitute לשמה?
lishma. It is enough. It is enough. That's why I said it's
a גזירה. gezeira Meaning until now the גמרא Gemara. has been very
clear that the לשמה התורף קאי lishma ha-toref kai only relates to
the essential part of the גט, get. not to the boilerplate. So
the read as we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara. of
Rabbi יהודה Yehuda is since, and this is what I was saying,
since there's a לשמה lishma. requirement and it's so critical,
we don't even want you to write the טופס tofes because that'll
come, because that'll just open up the door for you writing the
תורף שלא לשמה. toref she-lo lishma. Okay, but yes,
מדאורייתא mi-de-oraita nobody is debating that it's only a problem if the
תורף toref is written שלא לשמה, she-lo lishma, the names of the
people and we'll see another key line of הרי את מותרת, harei
at mutteret, we'll see that in a minute in the גמרא. Gemara
Everybody agrees that's the only לשמה lishma. requirement for Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer
if it's about the writing, not the signing. But nevertheless, the read
of Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer in the משנה mishna is I don't want
you even writing the טופס tofes part שלא לשמה she-lo lishma because
then it'll come to you to actually start filling in the name.
I guess conceptually my question is in the other direction. So לאה
Leah and ראובן Reuven are getting divorced. They're standing in front of
me, I write their name. Should it not be לשמה?
lishma Well, what do you mean? That was yesterday's משנה. mishna That
I'm just doing a practice גט get and I'm just using לאה
Leah or there's another person in the town that has a לאה
Leah and ראובן Reuven name. Now the other, right, now the other
possibility is which we've alluded to but haven't seen a direct discussion
yet is about the need for the ציווי הבעל. tzivuy ha-ba'al. That
if you're doing it on your own, right, you know,
which has not been in the משנה, mishna the משנה mishna has
not yet to say it, the משנה mishna. says you have to
write it for that man and that woman, the משנה mishna has
sounded like if I wrote it for the right ראובן Reuven and
לאה, Leah, right, you know,
that that actually would be okay if they wound up using it.
But the answer is it might not, even if you wrote it
for them, if the husband didn't direct you to do it, that
might not constitute לשמה. lishma. All right, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel: צריך שיניח אף מקום הרי את מותרת לכל אדם. tsarich
she-yaniach af makom harei at mutteret le-chol adam. He says, look, if
the, now it's clear at the end that Rabbi אליעזר's Eliezer issue
is a לשמה lishma. issue. It is not clear what the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma holds. Because the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma does not
distinguish גט get, from anything else, right? The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
just says whether it's a גט get or whether it's a loan
document or whether it's a bill of sale, you've got to leave
the blanks, you've got to don't fill in the blanks ahead of
time. So we don't know what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma, says.
There's nothing that indicates גט get, is special, right? So
it might not be. even the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, the whole need to leave blanks in the
document is a לשמה lishma need. And if it's a לשמה lishma
need, then you gotta have also לשמה lishma. and this has not
been said in any משנה mishna yet, but that if there's a
לשמה lishma requirement that applies not only to the unique features of
the גט, get the names and the and the date, but it
refers to the key line of the גט, get הרי את מותרת
לכל אדם. Harei at muteret le-chol adam. That's the punchline of the
גט. get Okay? So if we're saying וכתב לה ve-chatav lah means
וכתב לשמה, ve-chatav lishma, the גט get. has to be written לשמה,
lishma, why should I read that to be limited to just the
names? I mean, in a way, actually it's a חידוש chiddush to
say it doesn't mean the entire גט, get? right? Every single word
should have to be written לשמה. lishma. So the גמרא Gemara is
מחדש mechadesh though וכתב לה ve-chatav lah טופס קאי, tofes kai, it
means the essential part of the גט get? has to be written
לשמה. lishma So he says the essential part is not just the
names, the essential part is the key line that makes it a
גט, get? הרי את מותרת לכל אדם. Harei at muteret le-chol adam.
So he is reading that the משנה mishna is talking even the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, right? What it has to do with other
documents we'll find out. But even the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma the
leaving the blanks is because of a לשמה. lishma And if leaving
the blanks is a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and לשמה lishma issue,
then you gotta focus on the key punchline of the גט get
of הרי את מותרת לכל אדם Harei at muteret le-chol adam and
that has to be left blank as well so that can be
written לשמה. lishma צריכנא אף מקום הרי את מותרת לכל אדם כרבי
אליעזר היא דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי. Tzerichini af makom harei at muteret
le-chol adam k-Rabbi Eliezer hi de-amar edei mesirah karti. And even the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma. is going like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
says that you give it in front of witnesses that are present
at the time, you do not need to sign it. Since you
don't need to sign it, the essence of the גט get is
not its signatures, the essence of the גט get is the writing.
And since the essence is the writing, ובעינן כתיבה לשמה, u-beinan ketiva
lishma, it has to be written לשמה. lishma And that's why you
leave the blanks for the names and the date, and that's why
you better leave blank הרי את מותרת Harei at muteret because that's
the essence of the גט. get. So he's interpreting the משנה mishna.
to be according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that's why you leave
the blanks, and if that's true, you gotta leave הרי את מותרת
לכל אדם Harei at muteret le-chol adam unwritten as well. And now
the גמרא Gemara just gives a nice little summary of the last
few משניות mishnayot that have been dealing with this לשמה lishma issue.
Okay? וצריכא. Ve-tzricha. And if you were paying attention, רב יהודה אמר
שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel in three recent cases has clarified that
the משנה mishna, is going according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, and
holds about לשמה lishma by the writing. And you need to tell
it to me in all three cases. דאשמועינן בהך קמייתא, De-ashmueinan be-hakh
qamaitha, had he said with the first one, what was the first
one? The first one
was
מחובר, mechubar, that don't write it במחובר, be-mechubar, if you wrote it
במחובר be-mechubar and you tore it off and you gave it to
the woman, it's okay. So why, so if I can write it
במחובר be-mechubar and tear it off and sign it, that sounds like
actually I don't need the requirements are not in the writing, right?
Remember that משנה mishna. about מחובר? mechubar? Don't write it במחובר, be-mechubar,
if you wrote it במחובר be-mechubar then tear it off, sign it
and give it to the woman, you're okay. So that sounds like
that's a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir משנה. mishna So רב יהודה אמר
שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel said no no no, what the משנה
Mishna, means is, don't even write the boilerplate במחובר be-mechubar because you'll
come to actually write the essential part. If you wrote the boilerplate,
as long as you tore it off and then wrote the essential
part, the תורף toref when it was תלוש, talush, you're okay. So
he made that משנה Mishna רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. by saying that
the key is not signing versus writing, it's טופס tofes versus תורף.
toref. And he made that משנה Mishna of מחובר mechubar a רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. משנה. Mishna Okay, that was a more difficult reading
which is what the גמרא Gemara is saying. דאשמועינן בהך קמייתא, De-ashmueinan
be-hakh qamaitha,
I'm sorry wait, did I skip ahead?
Hold on one minute.
No, that's right,
I know let me just check
רש"י, Rashi. one minute.
Okay, דאשמועינן בהך קמייתא, De-ashmueinan be-hakh qamaitha, had he told us just
in the first case, that מחובר mechubar case, בהיא הוא דאיכא לאוקמה
כרבי אליעזר, ba-hi hu di-ika le-okmah ke-Rabbi Eliezer, that's why you can
say that it's going like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer דקתני אין כותבין,
de-ktani ein kotvin, don't write it במחובר, be-mechubar, וקתני כתב, u-ktani katav,
if you wrote it by מחובר, mechubar, so therefore it seems like
the problem was like with the writing. So therefore that was an
issue of you know
that it had to be written properly, of course although that's still
a hard read of the משנה, Mishna the emphasis at the beginning
of אין כותבין במחובר ein kotvin be-mechubar emphasizes that it's a writing
issue. But the end where it says if you wrote it tear
it off and sign it, that was a hard read like רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer. we said signing there didn't mean signing, hold on,
right. So
but anyway but that's how we chose, that's how we read the
end of the משנה. Mishna, The end of the משנה Mishna there
that we read was to say that it means that not if
you signed it after you tore it off, but if you wrote
the תורף toref after you tore it off.
And the סיפא seifa is influenced by the לשון. lashon. Alright, can
use my new eraser. Let me write, oh wow, that works well.
שכוח. Shkoiach. Okay, let me write the three cases so we can
appreciate.
You got a request for that eraser?
Some people in the דף daf just give nice gifts to their
רבי. Rebbe. So I'm gonna say anybody who has not yet done
that, you can surprise me. Okay, so there are three cases.
Case number one is אין כותבין במחובר. Ein kotvin bemuchbar.
כתבו במחובר פסול
חתמו ונתנו לה כשר.
Kasvu bemuchbar pasul chosmu venasnu
la kasher.
Okay,
that was case number one.
Case number two was case number two
was הכל כשרין לכתוב את הגט. Hakol ksherin lichtov et haget. הכל
כשרין לכתוב את הגט אפילו
Hakol
ksherin
lichtov et haget afilu חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh
shoteh
vekatan שאין
קיום
הגט אלא בחותמיו.
she-ein kiyum haget ela
bechotmav. And then the middle case was and then it's
אשה
כותבת את גיטה Isha kotevet et gita etc., and we have this
case which
is the case
about הכותב טופסי גיטין. Hakosev tofsay gittin,
Now,
you could have said that none of these were רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. Actually, it would have been actually a good read to read
most of these like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Don't write it במחובר,
bemuchbar, but if you did, in the end, as long as the
חתימה chasima was afterwards, you're okay. That sounds like a רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir position.
Why can everybody write a גט? get Why can a חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan write a גט? get, I thought you needed
לשמה. lishma. So that works actually okay if it's רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and it's about that the כתיבה ktiva doesn't matter, it's only
a חתימה chasima which is שאין קיום הגט אלא בחותמיו. ein kiyum
haget ela bechotmav. That works good according to
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. הכותב טופסי tofsei גיטין, gittin, you could say,
ah, well, if you need to leave blanks, that sounds like רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. But no, but it doesn't mention הרי את מותרת
לכל אדם. harei at muteret lechol adam. It doesn't mention the punchline.
It only mentions leaving blanks the particulars. So maybe there's some other
reason why you're supposed to leave it a blank, like because we'll
find out in a minute, but it's true by other שטרות, shtarot,
even by bills of sale, you leave the lines blank. So maybe
it has nothing to do with לשמה lishma, and it doesn't mention
הרי את מותרת. harei at muteret. So comes along רב ירמיה בר
שמואל Rav Yirmiyah bar Shmuel and he's so committed to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer. that he explains all these three משניות mishnayot to be
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer, That this doesn't mean the signing, what this
really means, he says, is you כותב תורף. kotev toref. That if
you were כתבו את התורף kasvu et hatoref
afterwards, you're okay, which is not פשט, pshat, but that's what he
says it means. Here he says הכל כשרין לכתוב את הגט, hakol
ksherin lichtov et haget, why? לכתוב את הגט, Lichtov et haget, he
says that means the טופס. tofes. Okay, and that's
why חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan can write it, as long
as you get an adult to write the תורף. toref. Again, not
פשט, pshat, reinterpreting it to be רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer Here, well,
what about the הרי את מותרת? harei at muteret? So he comes
along and he sticks
in also הרי את מותרת, harei at muteret, that that also has
to be.
So it's the כתיבה ktiva but you also need to leave the
הרי את מותרת. harei at muteret. So he modifies all three of
these cases in order to make it work like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer Okay.
So that is and then presumably it's because we פוסקין paskin like
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer So the גמרא Gemara is going to explain
to me
sort of what each one of them is a חידוש chiddush to
read it like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, but the גמרא Gemara is
going to say that it was like just because he was מחדש
mechadesh it in this משנה, Mishnah it might not it was like
maybe there was even more of a challenge to read it in
these other משניות. mishnayot. He had to sort
of emphasize that read in all these משניות mishnayot because there's something
in each משנה Mishnah that's sort of that argues against a רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer read.
Yes. Did you
say just because of the stature of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or
the
גמרא Gemara.
likes him להלכה, lehalacha,
the כתיבה ktiva as opposed like what
well, this is first of all, this is רב ירמיה בר שמואל.
Rav Yirmiyah bar Shmuel. If you remember, other אמוראים Amoraim read these
like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So it could just be like, okay,
the משנה Mishnah, isn't clear and we have to figure out which
תנא tanna it works by. But it also could be, are you
going to be more inclined by what's better the פשט pshat read
of the text of the משנה Mishnah, or are you going to
be more inclined by whose position you actually embrace להלכה? lehalacha? And
that could have a lot to do with it because we do
embrace רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. להלכה. lehalacha. Okay, although סתם משנה stam
Mishna is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Not only that, as the גמרא
Gemara is going to say, the end of the משנה Mishna says
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer. remember the end of this משנה, Mishna, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer פוסל בכולן poser bekulan. מכשיר
בכולן etc. So the fact that the end of the משנה Mishna
is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, makes it sound like the beginning is
not רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbi Eliezer. So there's a lot in
each of these משניות Mishnayot that speak against it being רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. So let's read that in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara? says like this.
וצריכה, U'tzricha, he needs to do this רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. even
tell it to me in all these three cases. If he just
said it in the first one, בהא הוא דאיכא למימר כרבי אליעזר.
be'ha hu d'ika l'meimar k'Rabbi Eliezer. Fine, that can work like רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer דקתני אין כותבין דקתני חתמו. d'katani ein kotvin d'katani
chatmu.
It emphasizes at least there's an issue with the writing. So even
though you have to reread here that when it's okay and it
says חתמו, chatmu, it doesn't mean signed, it means written to write
the תורף. toref. But nevertheless, the focus on the משנה Mishna is
that there are demands about the writing. And since that's the focus
of the מחובר mechubar משנה mishna that there are demands about the
writing, it's a reasonable read like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer even though
it requires rereading this word חתמו. chatmu. Okay, אבל סיפא דקתני שאין
קיום הגט אלא בחותמיו. aval seifa d'katani she'ein kiyum haget ela be'chotmav.
But this case, why can anybody write the גט? get I mean,
you could've also said that just the fact that it allows anybody
to write the גט get, speaks against רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. But
then saying that the reason anybody can write a גט get is
because it's all about the signing, that sounds very much like a
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir argument. Okay, אימא רבי מאיר היא דאמר עדי
חתימה כרתי. eima Rabbi Meir hi d'amar edei chatima kartei. That really
sounds like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So we're going to say, no,
no, it means don't write the תורף. toref. I mean, anybody can
write the תורף. toref. ואין קיום הגט אלא בחותמיו ve'ein kiyum haget
ela be'chotmav doesn't mean the signers, it means the people that are
physically present when it's given over. But come on, the fact that
there's a problem with the writing, I mean excuse me, there's no
problem with the writing, and it says it's all about the חתימה
chatima sounds a lot like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, so that really
requires some gymnastics to make that רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay. ואי
אשמעינן
בהא ההיא, v'ei ashmeinan be'ha he'i, if he just said that that's
a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, משנה, mishna. היכא דאיכא למימר כרבי אליעזר.
heicha d'ika l'meimar k'Rabbi Eliezer. אלא מדסיפא רבי אליעזר, ela mideseifa Rabbi
Eliezer, since רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer speaks out at the end of
our משנה, mishna אימא רישא
לאו רבי אליעזר. eima reisha lav Rabbi Eliezer.
So presumably the רישא reisha wouldn't be רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan that שמואל Shmuel wants to have all
three משניות Mishnayot going like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer And because this
is going like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, he has to stick in
that part, one of the things you leave blank is the key
line, the punchline of הרי את מותרת לכל אדם. harei at muteret
l'chol adam. Because if it's about לשמה, lishma. obviously the essence of
the גט get needs to be לשמה. lishma. Now about this punchline
of הרי את מותרת לכל אדם, harei at muteret l'chol adam, look
at this little תוספות. Tosafot. וצריך שיניח מקום הרי את מותרת לכל
אדם, v'tzarich sheyaniach makom harei at muteret l'chol adam, says
תוספות, Tosafot, דכל דוכתא משמע שכותבין לשון זה בגט, d'chol duchta mashma
she'kotvin lashon zeh b'get, right, I mean that's like the גט. get,
The גמרא Gemara is always saying הרי את מותרת לכל אדם harei
at muteret l'chol adam is עיקר הגט. ikar haget. ובפרק הבא נמי
תניא גופו של גט הרי את מותרת לכל
אדם.
u'veperek haba nami tanya gufo shel get harei at muteret
l'chol adam. והנה רבנו תם לכתוב לשון זה בגט. ve'hineh Rabbeinu Tam
lichtov lashon zeh b'get. So therefore, רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam started the
practice that when there are גיטין, gittin to include that line. The
fact that he had to start that practice meant that until רבנו
תם, Rabbeinu Tam, גיטין gittin did not have that line. How could
that be? So תוספות Tosafot says, well, that's what תוספות Tosafot is
asking. אבל בטופסי גיטין—and aval betofsei gittin here טופסי here does not
mean the non-essential part, here it just
means like the boilerplate, the standard language text of a
גט get. that predated רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, לא היו כותבין, lo
hayu kotvin, they did not have the words הרי את מותרת לכל
אדם. harei at muteret l'chol adam. You know, גיטין gittin. pre-רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam did not have those words. Okay. תוספות Tosafot ומכל מקום
אין להוציא לעז על גיטין הראשונים. u'mikol makom ein l'hotzi la'az al
gittin harishonim. Why I wanted you to see that? Remember that line
from an earlier גמרא? Gemara Right, just because we adopt new types
of stringencies, the גמרא Gemara once said we're not... we shouldn't be
adopting new stringencies, it raises questions about previous גיטין. gittin. But רבנו
תם Rabbeinu Tam said, well sometimes you gotta do it. Sometimes it
sounds like it's just so important that if we're going forward we
should... you know, we need to be saying הרי את מותרת לכל
אדם. harei at muteret l'chol adam. But you have to be careful
not to let that let you raise questions about the validity of
earlier גיטין. gittin, שהרי מאריכין לכתוב כמה לשונות בגט דחשיב כהרי את
מותרת לכל אדם. sheharei maarichin lichtov kama leshonot b'get d'chashiv k'harei at
muteret l'chol adam. There are a couple of, you know, other parallel
lines in the גט, get so it's not like there's magic in
those words if you articulate that idea with other words as well.
And if you remember, I read to you the language of the
גט get. that was printed in the רי"ף, Rif, like הרי... you
know... you know what is it... הרי תריכי לכי, I am divorcing
you, I am sending you away, and you are
permissible להתנסבא לכל גבר די תצביין. l'hitnasva l'chol gvar di titzviyan. You
can marry any man that you want. So you can marry any
man that you want is like הרי את מותרת לכל אדם. harei
at muteret l'chol adam. It's just said in Aramaic. So תוספות Tosafot
says we're not going to question, חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, earlier גיטין,
gittin but we're going to start using this language. Okay, so that's
interesting about that אין להוציא לעז. ein l'hotzi la'az.
Yes.
Do non-Ashkenazi גיטין Gittin have that language?
I'm sure by now they do. I'm sure. I don't know.
Okay, I mean the לשון lashon in the רי"ף, Rif, to me
when you read it, sounded like the obverse of the Aramaic of
a כתובה. kesuvah.
Yeah, well it was very... it was just the Aramaic language itself,
and yes, there definitely were a lot of parallels. Okay, yes.
I just want to understand, it's written here, but the רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam is saying it in the actual...
גיטין Gittin that were delivered in practice in the community prior רבינו
תם. Rabbeinu Tam. I don't know if all over the Jewish world,
only in אשכנז, Ashkenaz, and only wherever it was, but a lot
of existing גיטין gittin. right did not the standard נוסח הגט nusach
haget did not have the line of הרי את מותרת לכל אדם.
harei at muteseret lechol adam. In the גמרא Gemara it says that
sounds like that's the key line of a גט, get but somehow
now it might be that it was written in Aramaic which was
more the vernacular, right, although by the time of ראשוני אשכנז Rishonei
Ashkenaz Aramaic wasn't the vernacular anymore, but I don't know, anyway, yeah.
Why wasn't it written in French?
Exactly. You could. Okay, מפני תקנה. mipne takkana. Now
it says you leave these lines these things blank because of the
תקנה. takkana And remember the משנה mishna. is talking not just about
גט get even though we've argued that at least part of it
this is לשמה lishma? according to רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי תקנה mai takkana what's
this תקנה? takkana, אמר רב יונתן מפני תקנת סופר Amar Rav Yonasan
mipne takkanas sofer for רבי אליעזר היא דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי. Rabbi
Eliezer hi d'amar edei mesira karsi. Okay, it means to make life
easier for the סופר sofer to let them to pre-write these forms
so we've given him a latitude to do it and now why
did we need to give him a תקנה takkana a latitude to
do it? Why shouldn't he be able to do it? He's you
know what's the problem? So the point is there is a problem.
It's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, who needs כתיבה לשמה kshiva lishma and
therefore I might have wanted to be very protective of not pre-writing
any part of the גט get. because it might lead to לשמה
lishma problems, but because of תקנת הסופרים takkanas hasoferim to make life
easier for the סופרים sofrim I'm going to let them write the
boilerplate part. Okay, ובדין הוא דאפילו טופס נמי לא ליכתוב. uvidin hu
d'afillu tofes nami lo lichteiv. Once you're in a רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer world and you're dealing with a גט, get we shouldn't really
even let you write the boilerplate because you'll come to write the
actual
essence you know הרי את מותרת harei at muteseret or something else
שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. ומשום תקנת סופרים שרו רבנן Umishum takkanas sofrim
sharu rabanan the Rabbis allowed, okay, and so that's the first position.
We allow you to do it and leave the line blank and
we're not afraid you're going to do it שלא לשמה. shelo lishma.
Now the other thing is though but by other שטרות, shtaros,
right, we why don't we let you fill in the blanks of
other שטרות? shtaros? So again within a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer world
the answer is well we don't let you do it in other
שטרות shtaros because you'll come to do it by גט. get So
basically it starts like this. We're in a לשמה lishma. world a
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer we've got a problem, you certainly by גט
get. cannot fill in the blanks you know before it's time. Okay,
but what we're going to do is we will continue to allow
you to do the boilerplate. We won't make a גזירה gezeira on
the boilerplate, but what where we will make a גזירה is that
by other שטרות shtaros you also can't fill in the blank. Okay,
because if you come to fill in the blank by other שטרות
shtaros you'll come to fill it in by a גט. get That's
the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma Okay, and then comes רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda פוסל בכולן. He doesn't allow other שטרות shtaros or even a
גט get. to even be the boilerplate. גזר טופס אטו תורף Gazar
tofes atu toreif by a גט get. he doesn't want you to
do the boilerplate because you'll come to fill in the lines and
וגזר שטרות אטו גיטין vegazar shtaros atu gittin and he doesn't want
you to do other שטרות shtaros even the boilerplate because it'll come
to filling in the lines the תורף toreif of a גט. get
Okay, so the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says both תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda agree שטרות shtaros and גט get
are the same, but we're making שטרות shtarot like גט get to
protect גט. get For the תנא קמא tanna kamma we're only saying
by גט get no תורף, toreif, טופס tofes is okay by גט.
get We won't bother to protect that, we have רחמנות rachmanus on
the סופרים sofrim and we'll say the same by שטרות shtarot to
protect גט. get And רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says I'm not going
to allow anything to be done ahead of time, not by a
גט get I'm not going to allow anything because I'm afraid you'll
come to fill in the blanks you'll do the תורף toreif and
once I'm not allowing it by a גט get I'm not going
to allow by other שטרות shtaros either. That's רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda.
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer. the final רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. of the
משנה, mishna the beginning of the משנה mishna? was שיטת רבי אליעזר,
shittas Rabbi Eliezer, but the other רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer himself by
the end of the משנה Mishnah, מכשיר בכולן חוץ מגיטי נשים. mashir
bekulan chutz migittei nashim.
He says by other שטרות shtarot no problem. It's not a לשמה
lishma, issue, fill it in געזונטהייט, gezunteheit, I have no problem what
you do by other שטרות. shtarot. But by גיטי נשים gittei nashim
I don't even allow you to do the boilerplate. Okay, טופס אטו
תורף גזר. tofes atu toreif gazar.
So by the גט get itself I'm not allowing you to write
the boilerplate because you'll come to do the תורף. toreif. Okay, שטרות
אטו גיטין לא גזר shtaros atu gittin lo gazar but other שטרות
shtarot do whatever you want. All right? So you have the first
two positions says שטרות shtaros parallels גט get? and but the concern
is a גט get, concern. So position one is you can do
the טופס tofes don't do the תורף, toreif, that's true about גט
get it's true about שטרות. shtaros. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says don't
do anything by גט get, I'm very protective about גט get and
once you don't do anything by גט get don't do anything by
other שטרות. shtaros. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. says שטרות shtaros do
whatever the heck you want. גט get that's about לשמה lishma, don't
even do the טופס. tofes. Okay, that's how we explain the three
positions within the world of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer All right, good?
Yes? Okay.
Does the whole concept of רבי אליעזר שמותו Rabbi Eliezer shmuto in
any way affect his הלכה? halacha? Not here.
Not here. Ah, yes it does, but not here.
It's localized in other words?
Well, I don't know, some it does actually, but here, here we're
very happy with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer שנאמר וכתב לה. shene'emar vechatav
la. והא כי כתב לה אטורף הוא דכתיב. V'ha ki katav la
a'toref hu d'chtiv.
Why does the משנה mishna say that the problem, that the and
by saying רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. says it says וכתב לה vechatav
la so you can't even write the boiler plate? But וכתב לה
vechatav la only refers to the טורף, toref, the essentials, the names
and as שמואל Shmuel told us הרי את מותרת. harei at muteret.
So why is he using that to tell me don't even write
the boiler plate by a גט? get So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא אימא משום שנאמר
וכתב לה
לשמה.
ela eima mishum shene'emar vechatav la
lishma. Wait, what's that אלא
אימא?
ela eima?
Oh, don't say שנאמר, shene'emar say משום שנאמר וכתב לה לשמה. mishum
shene'emar vechatav la lishma. שנאמר shene'emar, means that it is a direct
application of the verse. Okay, שנאמר וכתב לה לשמה shene'emar vechatav la
lishma means a direct application of the לשמה lishma requirement is you
can't write the טופס. tofes. That's not true. But משום שנאמר mishum
shene'emar is an indirect application of the verse. Because there's a לשמה
lishma, issue about the טורף, toref, we're not even going to let
you write the טופס. tofes. All right? Everybody get it? So וכתב
לה vechatav la is just telling you don't write the טורף toref
שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. But if it just said שנאמר, well the
פסוק pasuk doesn't tell me I can't write the טופס, tofes, but
משום שנאמר mishum shene'emar means based on the concerns of the פסוק
pasuk I'm not even going to let you write the טופס. tofes.
Okay, so that's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer's Now the גמרא Gemara says
קשיא דרבי אליעזר אדרבי אליעזר. kashya d'Rabbi Eliezer a'd'Rabbi Eliezer. So the
תנא קמא you said was according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
he was okay with the טופס. tofes. The end is רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and he's not okay with the טופס. tofes. So it's
a contradiction of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer So תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי
אליעזר, trei tanna'ei aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer, two תנאים tanna'im debating what רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer. position would be. Okay, but that's the whole thing
within the world of a רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer. and שלא לשמה.
shelo lishma. The whole problem starts with גט, get the whole need
to leave the blanks plus as שמואל Shmuel adds הרי את מותרת
harei at muteret is לשמה. lishma And then the question is how
much does that spread out to other שטרות shtarot and how much
does that spread out to the טופס tofes as well? Okay, that's
one read of the משנה. mishna. רב שבתאי אמר חזקיה, Rav Shabtai
amar Chizkiya,
רב שבתאי Rav Shabtai says in the name of חזקיה, Chizkiya, משום
קטטה. mishum ketata. This has nothing to do until you get to
the last line of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and לשמה, lishma the
leaving of the blanks has nothing to do with לשמה. Lishmah Because
think about it, the beginning of the משנה mishna treats גט get
like any other שטר. shtar. It just says you leave the blanks.
So it has nothing to do with לשמה. Lishmah So why do
you leave the blanks if according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it
has nothing to do with לשמה? Lishmah Because of fights. Because basically
you don't want the wife or the husband, well I guess it'd
be the wife because she would be the only one who could
be done without her knowledge, walking by and hearing a סופר sofer
pre-filling out a גט, get okay, with her name in it and
saying to herself what, oh my god, it sounds like my husband
has told a סופר sofer to write a גט get. for me.
Okay? So you don't want and in general, it's like it's just
not good policy to have a document pre-filled out, okay? Even if
you say it's not kosher until it gets signed and it's not
a לשמה Lishmah problem, you know, don't say, you know, sorry I'm
just going to have a document that says that you borrowed a
million dollars from me just pre-filled out, I'm going to pay a
סופר sofer today, don't worry, I'm not signing witnesses yet. Right?
I'm going to have a סופר sofer fill me out a document
that I just bought your house. Don't worry, don't worry, it's not
valid yet, there are no witnesses on it, right? Like nobody wants
documents pre-filled out that affect them, okay, it's just not good policy.
All right? So that's what he says. That's what's going on in
the משנה. mishna It's nothing to do with לשמה. Lishmah רבי מאיר
היא דאמר עדי חתימה כרתי. Rabbi Meir hi d'amar edei chatima katrei.
ובדין הוא דאפילו תורף נמי נכתוב U'vidin hu d'afilu toref nami nichtov
and really there's really no real problem filling in the blanks by
a גט get, or other documents. וזימנין דשמע לה לסופר דקא כתיב,
v'zimnin d'shama lah l'sofer d'ka kativ, but the woman sometimes hears a
סופר sofer writing a גט get, with her name in it וסברה
איהו קאמר ליה, v'savra ihu ka'amar leh, she thinks the husband told
the סופר sofer to do this והויא לה קטטה בהדיה v'havya lah
ketata bahadei and then they'll lead to fights in the home. So
that's why. So the משום תקנה mishum takkana is not תקנת סופרים.
takkunat sofrim. And משום תקנה mishum takkana is not why we allow
you to write the boiler plate. משום תקנה mishum takkana is why
we don't let you fill in the blanks. In principle, whether a
גט get or other שטרות shtarot you could fill in the blanks,
it's all about the signing. But you know what? Because of the
תקנה, takkana we're telling people don't fill in the blanks. תקנת קטטה.
takkunat ketata. It's just not good policy. Okay. ורב חסדא אמר אבימי
משום תקנת עגונות. V'Rav Chisda amar Avimi mishum takkunat agunot. Now the
other, so one explanation was תקנת קטטה, takkunat ketata, one was תקנת
סופרים. takkunat sofrim. He says it's because of תקנת עגונות. takkunat agunot.
Which way does this work? Does this work with the רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer read of the משנה mishna, or the רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir read of the משנה? mishna So the גמרא Gemara says you
could go both ways. אמרי לה רבי מאיר ואמרי לה רבי אליעזר.
Amri lah Rabbi Meir v'amri lah Rabbi Eliezer. Some say according to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, some say according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer
אמרי לה רבי מאיר Amri lah Rabbi Meir that in principle you
should be able to write everything, right? So the תקנה takanah is
telling you don't fill in the blanks. דאמר עדי חתימה כרתי d'amar
edei chatima katrei that it goes by the signing. ובדין הוא דאפילו
תורף נמי נכתוב u'vidin hu d'afilu toref nami nichtov and in principle
you should be able to even fill in the blanks. So the
תקנה takanah according Rabbi Meir is saying don't fill in the blanks.
Okay, וזימנין, ve-zimnin, so now but here's the עגונה agunah problem about
if you were to fill in the blanks. וזימנין דהוי ליה קטטה
בהדה, ve-zimnin de-havih lei ktatah bahadah, not that it'll he'll hear it
and it'll lead to a fight. But you know what? Look, I'm
living in this town. There are only twenty couples in this town
and might as well just pre-write twenty גיטין. gittin Okay? You know,
so he'll have a גט get, ready if anybody ever needs a
divorce. 'Hi, mate of divorce, I'll just pre-write the twenty גיטין gittin
that are necessary for this town in case any of them need
it. It'll give me some good practice.' That's תקנת עגונות, takanat agunot,
because then there'll be people who'll have a fight and the guy
will storm off, run into the סופר sofer store, and he'll be
able to get his גט get in two seconds. Okay? So that's
going to lead to a woman getting divorced, you know, when they
should have worked it out. Okay, which is interesting that the גמרא
Gemara calls it עגונה, agunah, right? Yeah, really interesting. So it says,
וזימנין דהוי ליה קטטה בהדה, ve-zimnin de-havih lei ktatah bahadah, they'll have
a
fight, ורהט ואייתי וזרק לה, ve-rahat ve-ayti ve-zarak lah, and he'll throw
it to her. Now, of course, he wouldn't be able to just
throw it to her, he needs to get witnesses to sign, but
the point is, you know, if the גט get is all pre-written
and all you need is to sign witnesses, okay, then that'll lead
to her to get divorced very quickly without them resolving it. ומעגן
ומושב לה, u-meagen u-moshiv lah, and she'll be a עגונה agunah and,
you know, and like she'll be left an עגונה. agunah. In a
what way is she left an עגונה? agunah? So look at רש"י.
Rashi רש"י Rashi says, ומעגן ומושב לה u-meagen u-moshiv lah כשהיא מגורשת.
keshi-hi megureshet. רש"י Rashi's just says, you know, a woman who is
left, who without a, in those societies, without a husband, without a
household, without somebody providing her support is sort of like a little
bit, you know,
I mean the עגונה agunah in the sense of chained to her
husband is not true, but she is sort of in a like
less than, you know, very disadvantaged societal position. Okay, which she didn't
need to have this because they could have worked it out. And
it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara does sort of call that עגונה.
agunah. Yes.
So I submit myself to רש"י Rashi wisdom and authority, but... Yes...
That's not what the תלמוד Talmud says. The תלמוד Talmud says he
just throws it down and storms off.
So you mean he doesn't sign witnesses to her?
That's what the גמרא Gemara says and he storms off and that's
it, he can't take it anymore and she's left, she's not מגורשת
megureshet and she's an עגונה. agunah.
Yeah, I'm not sure that the גמרא Gemara would... so it's a
good question. The גמרא Gemara. clearly here is using עגונה agunah more
broadly. Question is what do you think? That the גמרא Gemara is
using עגונה agunah for a woman who feels like emotionally abandoned but
not actually, you know, in any legal status that has changed, you
know, nothing has changed.
I don't read it that... I get that... If you...
but I understand what you're reading it, but you're saying he throw
her the גט. get Why is she an עגונה? agunah? Then when
he calms down, he realizes, 'Oh, she's not divorced, no problem.'
I don't have any calming down here. He's רותח roteiach and that's
it.
You're just saying that the throwing of the גט, get, even an
unsigned גט, get, will leave the marriage shattered in a way. Sort
of like once you say certain things, you can't take them back.
So just... And that's it, he moved.
He went to LA. She...
he didn't give her a...
Ah, it's not a real
מסירה. mesirah. I see. Right.
Right.
An invalid גט get floating around that someone feels like they could
just hand to their wife and it's not complete.
I see. That's interesting. That's an interesting read. some... No, no, no,
I hear you. It's an interesting read. It's more consistent with the
idea of עגונה. agunah. Okay, I hear it. Okay, so that's one
read, that it's according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the תקנה
takana is don't fill in the blanks, it's too dangerous having pre-filled
גיטין Gittin, floating around. Okay, that's the עגונה agunah problem. אמרי לה
רבי אלעזר Amri leh Rabbi Elazar and some say it's רבי אלעזר.
Rabbi Elazar. So according to רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, the תקנה takana
is that we let you write the boilerplate. דאמרי עדי מסירה כרתי,
d'amri edei mesirah kratei, ובדין הוא דאפילו טופס נמי לא לכתוב, u-vidin
hu d'afilu tofes nami lo lichtov,
we shouldn't let you write the boilerplate because that's going to lead
to לא לשמה lo lishma problems. וזימנין דבעי למיזל למדינת הים, ve-zimnin
d'ba'ei lemeizal limdinat hayam, but the problem is if you don't have
a boilerplate pre-written, then there are times that the husband has to
go far to an overseas, okay, and he wants to give his
wife a גט, get like maybe a conditional גט get if he
doesn't return, right? Because if he doesn't come back in two years,
there's been no information, that's a real עגונה agunah situation. So he
wants to give his wife a conditional גט get like if I
don't come back in a year, in two years, or whatever, you're
divorced, right?
But he doesn't have time to prepare the גט get because you
have to write it from scratch. Okay, so ולא אשכח ספרא, ve-lo
ashcach safra,
he won't find a סופר sofer to write the whole גט, get,
ושביק לה, ve-shavik lah, and he'll just leave on his trip without
giving her this גט, get ואזיל, ve-azil, and he'll leave, ומעגן ומושב
לה, u-meagen u-moshiv lah, and she'll be left an עגונה. agunah. Okay,
so there's a תקנת עגונות takanat agunot to be able to, A,
not have the גט get fully filled out because then she'll be
given a גט get, and she'll be unnecessarily divorced, or according to
what Rav Dov said, she'll be given the גט get and she'll
like effectively be divorced without really being divorced, but he'll have abandoned
her. But there's also תקנת עגונות takanat agunot of not making it
too difficult to give a גט get, when a גט get is
necessary, right? And that's like I think a lot how we think
about עגונה agunah nowadays. The way we think about עגונה agunah is
to expedite the giving of the גט, get. to make it, to
make it, to make the giving of the גט get, possible when
it's necessary. Okay, but anyway in terms of פשט pshat of the
משנה, Mishna, there's two פשטים. pshatim. Okay. One is leave the lines
blank to protect for לשמה, Lishmah and then, so obviously you gotta
leave the lines blank, okay, and then the only issue is are
we going to also say don't even do the תופס, tofes, okay,
or are we because we want to protect לשמה, Lishmah, or are
we going to for for certain תקנות takanos reasons we'll allow you
to write the תופס tofes for the sake of the סופר sofer
and for the sake of an עגונה. aguna. And the other read
of the משנה Mishnah is not that we need a תקנה takana,
to let you write the תופס, tofes, but
we need a תקנה to tell you don't fill in the blanks.
Why not fill in the blanks? It's not signed yet. No, you
fill in the blanks, it leads to fights, it leads to people
throwing a גט get before they really should be giving a גט,
get et cetera, et cetera. Don't pre-fill in any blanks. Okay, so
that's how to read the משנה. Mishnah Is the משנה being מחדש
mechadesh not to fill in the blanks because of a תקנה, but
in principle you should be able to, like רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir,
or is the משנה being מחדש mechadesh it's okay to do the
boiler plate even though there are לשמה lishma issues and it's going
like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
This גט get is תנאי tnai for the business trip, it's dated
from when he leaves, it's not מאוחר, me'uchar, right? It's not.
What do you mean מאוחר? You mean מוקדם? mukdam. Yeah. Well, that's
yeah, I mean, that's what we're going to get to that, that's
actually coming up next, why do you leave the time blank. Okay,
ומקום הזמן. So the other thing you leave blank is the date.
And that's like an obvious reason you leave the date blank is
because, you know, even if it's not even let's just talk about
a normal שטר, shtar, right? I know, you know, I call up
the סופר sofer and I say, right, like, you know, I'm trying
to borrow a thousand dollars from Charlie, if I get him to
say yes, I need the שטר shtar like ready to go so
he doesn't, you know, he doesn't dilly dally once he's agreed to
lend me the money. Can you prepare the שטר? shtar? So he
prepares the שטר shtar and he says Dov borrowed a thousand dollars
from Charlie, but he's got to leave the blank, and even if
that's okay, we can fill in those blanks, right? Even if that
wasn't an
issue, but there's no way you can pre-fill in the date because
if he pre-fills in the date, I might not get him to
agree for a week from now, and if the date was today,
right? Then that means that he would have liens on my property
a week before I actually borrowed the money. And that's a מוקדם.
Same by a גט, get if the date was before it was
given, you the woman would be perceived as of being divorced before
she was actually divorced. So whatever the reasons are about not filling
in the blanks for שטר, shtar, whether it's protecting a שטר shtar
אטו atu גט get and protecting about לשמה, whether it's about fight
and just it's dangerous to have things floating around, not filling in
the other blanks, it's clear why you have to leave the date
blank because you can't have a pre-dated שטר shtar and you can't
have a pre-dated גט. get Okay, so that's מקום הזמן. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara פסיק ותני. pasik vetani. So
the משנה, you know, does not differentiate and it teaches: לא שנא
מן הנשואין ולא שנא מן האירוסין. lo shna min hanisuin velo shna
min ha'eirusin. Whether it's a divorce and it's only was only after
whether it was after נשואין, nisuin, after we've been living together, or
whether it's only after the קידושין kiddushin and we haven't yet been
living together, and hasn't yet been a חופה, chuppa, you know, either
way you need a גט, get and either way it's a problem
of writing the date. Pre-dating is a problem. So the משנה says
like this:
בשלמא, bishlama, בשלמא מן הנשואין, bishlama min hanisuin, I get why there's
a problem of having an earlier date if they're divorcing from נשואין,
nisuin, בין למאן דאמר משום בת אחותו איכא בין למאן דאמר משום
פירי איכא. bein leman d'amar mishum bas achoso ika bein leman d'amar
mishum peiri ika.
Remember the debate about why you have a date in a גט
get. and why it can't be pre-dated? One reason is because
a man's wife commits adultery, he might want to save her from
being executed by the court because he loves her, maybe he loves
her because it's his niece, that was the case. Otherwise, maybe he'd
be angry that she got I'm sorry, either way he's angry she
committed adultery, anyway, but okay, but at least in that case he
has some remaining רחמנות. rachmanus. Alright, so therefore he wants to make
it look like she got divorced before she actually did. So that
would be relevant even if it was מן האירוסין, min ha'eirusin, right?
You don't want a pre-dated גט get if she were to commit
adultery after whatever, you know, you don't want it to look like
she was divorced before she was divorced. Fine. That's one case in
terms of that. But how about if the concern is that we
don't want it pre-dated because from the moment I divorce her, I
lose my rights
in the what do you call it? In getting the פירות נכסי
מלוג. peiros nichsei melog. So if there's no date, I'll claim that
I only divorced her today and I'll be eating those פירות peiros
שלא כדין. shelo k'din. If it's
pre-dated, then she'll have rights, then
she'll get rights to the פירות peiros before she's entitled to that
and maybe it's all part of some scheme against people that I
would have sold those פירות peiros to. So because of those concerns
about making it clear who owns those פירות נכסי מלוג peiros nichsei
melog in what stage, it has to have a date and it
has to have the right date. But all of that only starts
when am I entitled to the נכסי מלוג? nichsei melog? נשואין, nisuin,
not from קידושין. kiddushin. So the גמרא's Gemara's asking basically ask the
question why do I care about the date if they're only getting
divorced. מן האירוסין. min ha'erusin. Okay, if the issue is the פירות.
peiros. If the issue is about adultery and misrepresenting when she was
divorced, that's always a concern. If the issue is about the פירות,
peiros, date should not be an issue if they're only, if they
never, if there never was נישואין, nissuin, because then he was never
entitled to the פירות. peiros. So let's take a look.
בשלמא Bishlama מן הנישואין, min hanissuin, בין למאן דאמר משום בת אחותו
איכא, bein leman d'amar mishum bas achoso ika, בין למאן דאמר משום
פירי איכא. bein leman d'amar mishum peiri ika. אלא מן האירוסין, Ella
min ha'erusin, if it's only, if it's a divorce after אירוסין, erusin,
בשלמא למאן דאמר משום בת אחותו איכא, bishlama leman d'amar mishum bas
achoso ika, if it's about a concern about adultery and misrepresenting when
she was divorced, that's an issue even
מן האירוסין. min ha'erusin. אלא למאן דאמר משום פירי, Ella leman d'amar
mishum peiri, but if the whole issue of date is to know
who owns the פירות peiros of the נכסי מלוג nichsei melog when,
so ארוסה מי אית לה פירי? arusa mi is lah peiri? Why
do you need a date and why is having a pre-dated שטר
גט shtar get not good if it's only מן האירוסין? min ha'erusin?
So that's a pretty good question. So unless you can just say
לא פלוג, lo plug, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר רב עמרם הא מילתא שמיע לי מיניה דעולא, Amar Rav Amram
ha milsa shamia li minei d'Ulla, you know what? I heard this
teaching from עולא, Ulla, דאמר משום תקנת ולד. d'amar mishum takanas valad.
He says the reason it's important to not have a pre-dated גט
get, even מן האירוסין, min ha'erusin, even ignoring adultery, is for the
sake of the child. Okay, ולא ידענא מאי ניהו, v'lo yadana mai
nihu, I didn't know what he was talking
about. כיון דשמעתיה להא דתניא, Kivan d'shamasei l'ha d'tanya, once I heard
that ברייתא, braita, האומר כתבו גט לארוסתי, ha'omer kisvu get l'arusasi, so
here's another case of a גט get for an ארוסה. arusa. Write
this גט get for the woman I just betrothed, לכשאכנסנה אגרשנה, lechshe'echnesena
agarshena,
after our wedding night I'll divorce her. Okay, so you know, he
maybe just wants to have sex with her or whatever. Let's pre-write
a גט get. and I'll divorce her soon after we actually do
the חופה. chuppah. I just did קידושין, kiddushin, soon after the חופה.
chuppah. So can you do that? Can you write a גט get
from אירוסין erusin to use after נישואין? nissuin? So the הלכה halacha
is אינו גט, eino get, it's not valid. Now, why is it
not valid? So ואמר עולא מה טעם, v'amar Ulla mah ta'am, why
is it not valid? דאורייתא De'oraisa really it is a good גט.
get It's דרבנן, derabbanan, it's funny, the phrase אינו גט eino get
for something that's only a דרבנן derabbanan problem. But here's why not:
גזירה שמא יאמרו גיטה קודם לבנו. gzeira shema yomru gita kodem livno.
Because what will happen if we let the guy, other than the
fact that he's obviously mis-, tremendously abusing, mistreating this woman, I don't
know, maybe she's in on it, anyway, but the problem is is
that the גט get will be dated from before the נישואין, nissuin,
right? What will happen? They'll have the wedding night together, maybe, maybe
she'll get pregnant, then or, you know, maybe they'll spend a week
together, then he'll give her the גט, get then she'll have a
child. People will look at the גט Get. and they'll see: wait
a minute, it looks like she was, the date on the גט
Get. will be from the time of אירוסין, erusin, right? Even though
it was given after נישואין. nissuin. So people will say, whoa, you
mean your kids were born out of wedlock? Now they're not ממזרים,
mamzerim, okay, that doesn't really change their הלכה halachic status, but as
רש''י says, it's still a פגם משפחה. pegam mishpacha. It looks like,
you know, you know, people will perceive it that the, that the
kids were born after the גט. get, So therefore, in order to
protect the woman and her reputation and the kids' reputations, we don't
allow a גט Get to be, that was written pre-נישואין nissuin to
be given after נישואין. nissuin. Okay, so that's that issue. So if
that's true, he says הכא נמי גזירה שמא יאמרו גיטה קודם לבנה.
hacha nami gzeira shema yomru gita kodem livna.
Same issue here. Meaning, if he wrote it and gave it to
her while she was still an ארוסה, arusa, it really wouldn't matter
that it's pre-dated. What do I care? Okay, it was dated January
or March, either way she's an ארוסה. arusa. If I'm not afraid
of adultery, what, what difference does it make at which, whether, you
know, whether it took place in January or in March? There's no
פירות, peiros, it's all ארוסה, arusa, that wouldn't have been an issue.
But here's why you don't write the date of a גט Get.
for an ארוסה arusa prior to the actual time it's ready to
be given. Because maybe he won't use it until the נישואין. nissuin.
And if he holds it and keeps it in his pocket and
doesn't use it until the נישואין, nissuin, then it's going to look
bad that it's dated from the time that she was an ארוסה.
arusa. All right, so is that clear? We don't want a גט
get, that is an early date prior to the time it was
given. If there's an adultery concern, that's clear why not, we don't
want it to misrepresent when she was divorced. If it's a פירות
peiros concern, it's not clear why we care if she was only
an ארוסה, arusa, that's only a נישואין nissuin issue. And the גמרא's
Gemara answer is, you know what, really you're right. If it's going
to be given while she's an ארוסה, arusa, in principle we shouldn't
care and we don't care, really, that it was pre-dated. But the
reason we don't want to write it for a woman as an
ארוסה arusa if he's not ready to give it yet is because
he might not give it till she's a נשואה. nesua. And then
it'll look like the kids were born out of wedlock. Okay, so
that's the issue.
אמר רבי זירא
אמר רב אבא בר שילא אמר רב המנונא סבא אמר רב אדא
בר אהבה אמר רב הלכה כרבי אלעזר. Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav
Abba bar Shila amar Rav Hamnuna Saba amar Rav Adda bar Ahava
amar Rav halacha k'Rabbi Elazar. We rule like רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
which means we rule that לשמה by גט get. and עידי מסירה
כרתי, eidei mesira karsai, which the גמרא Gemara says elsewhere. That's really
important by גיטין, Gittin, that the ruling is עידי מסירה כרתי, eidei
mesira karsai, which also, which means for us the heavy לשמה requirements
and the heavy כתיבה ksiva requirements. But also saying we rule like
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar means רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar at the end
of the משנה, which means that you don't even write... the טופס.
Tofes. Right? Until now we've been saying, oh, okay, you write the
טופס, Tofes, חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh Shoteh v'Katan, or write it במחובר
בדיעבד, b'Mechuber b'Di'eved, this, that, whatever. Here, the רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
remember at the end of the משנה says, by גיטין, it's all
פסול. pasul. I'm so demanding of לשמה that I am going to
protect the לשמה of the טופס Tofes and tell you, don't even
write the טופס. Tofes. So according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer... of
the משנה if we rule like him, you cannot even write the
boiler plate of the גט. get, Okay, because he wants to protect
the לשמה of the גט. get That's one part. But the other
part of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, is, he was happy to have
you fill out a שטר shtar ahead of time as long as
you didn't sign it. Right? Remember the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer בשאר
שטרות b'sha'ar shtaros do whatever you want. Fill it all out. I
don't care. Don't sign it yet obviously, but you can fill it
out ahead of time. So now the גמרא's Gemara, going to shift
its attention to the שאר שטרות sha'ar shtaros part of רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer... Let's take a
look. Okay. קרי רב עליה דרבי אלעזר טובינא דחכימי. Kari Rav alei
d'Rabbi Elazar Tuveina d'Hakimi. So as opposed to the whole שמותי Shmuti
point, here he calls him the best of the sages. Okay, so
that's that's רב אל... Rab El... wait, it's by the way, no,
no, דב, Dov, you were מס... mis... you were confusing me. This
is רב אלעזר. Rab Elazar. This is a student of...
I was going to...
yeah, yeah, yeah, I noticed you say רבי אליעזר...
Rabbi Eliezer You're right.
רב אלעזר. Rab Elazar. רבי
אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Right, right. So it's my fault. I've been mispronouncing.
Right, this is a student of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. It's a
colleague of רבי Rebbe. יהודה and רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. It's not,
no, no, the רבי Rebbe. אליעזר, no, no, the רבי אליעזר that
שמותי, Shmuti, that's רבי עקיבא's... Rabbi Akiva that's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
רבי. Right, right. This is רב אלעזר. Rab Elazar. רב אלעזר. Rab
Elazar.
Wasn't it one from the last מסכת Masechet where you said at
one point that even there were different ריי... ri... different versions, one
that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and רבי אליעזר...
Well, it's normally distinguished. So anyway, so I've been...
in this מסכת Masechet should be אלעזר. Elazar. Yeah, yeah.
The רב אלעזר Rab Elazar about the לשמה is רב אלעזר. Rab
Elazar. So I apologize. You have to go back and edit all
the previous three weeks and go change... right, we'll do a search
and replace of audio search and replace...
contemporary רבי מאיר... Rabbi Meir...
Right, right. רב אלעזר, Rab Elazar, רבי יהודה, רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
those were all contemporaries, all students of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. The
רבי אליעזר of שמותי, Shmuti, that was רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva רבי.
All right, fine. Moving on. Moving on. Okay. Anyway, so we rule
like רב אלעזר. Rab Elazar. Can't believe you people. We rule like
רב אלעזר Rab Elazar that we require that it's about עדי מסירה
כרתי, Eidei Mesirah Karti, we require לשמה and that you can't even
write the טופס Tofes and קרי רב עליו דרבי אלעזר, Kari Rav
alav d'Rabbi Elazar, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said about רב אלעזר, Rab
Elazar, טובינא דחכימי. Tuveina d'Hakimi. He's the best of the sages. אה.
Ah. Now the גמרא Gemara says: ועשינו בשאר שטרות נמי? V'asinu b'sha'ar
shtaros nami? Do we also rule like him by other שטרות shtaros
לקולא l'kula that you can pre-fill out an entire שטר, shtar, just
don't sign it? That's what he says, even with the names and
all the whole thing? That's okay? ואמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא, V'amar
Rav Pappa mishmei d'Rava, but רב פפא Rav Pappa says in the
name of
רבא, Rava, האי אשורתא דדייני, hai astrata d'dayanei, the... the... what do
you call it, like the validation of the דיינים dayanim when they
validate signatures, like what's that called, like when they notarize, you know,
the signatures, so
דמיכתבא מקמי דליתו סהדי ויחתמימו ידייהו, d'michtiva mikmi d'leisai sahadei v'yachsimum yadai,
before the witnesses have testified to their signatures, I mean, this גט,
this whatever it is, it's a שטר shtar that says ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon signed the שטר. shtar. ראובן and שמעון are standing
in בית דין Beis Din ready to testify that it's their signature.
They've shown up. We know they're about to testify, but they haven't
officially submitted their testimony yet that it's their signatures. You know what
we're going to do? We're just going to save time and we're
just going to pre-write our... our notarization on the signatures before they've
officially testified. Okay, we won't sign it yet, but we'll like pre-write
our notarization and won't sign it until we hear their
testimony. Okay. So האי אשורתא דדייני דמיכתבא, hai astrata d'dayanei d'michtiva, that
was written מקמי דליתו סהדי ויחתמימו ידייהו mikmi d'leisai sahadei v'yachsimum yadai
before they've testified to their signatures, פסולה, psulah, it's invalid because you
don't write something even if you wait to sign it before it's
time. That's considered to be a type of a מחזי כמזויף. mechezi
k'mizuyaf. It looks forged. You're writing it before it's true. Okay. So
אמר מחזי כשקרא. ama mechezi k'shikra. I'm sorry, מחזי כשקרא. mechezi k'shikra.
So therefore we don't write things even if we wait to sign
them before they're true. So הכא נמי נחזי כשקרא. hacha nami nechezi
k'shikra. How can we pre-fill out a document even if we don't
sign it before it's ready? It looks like it's a
lie. So but the גמרא, Gemara, you know what the גמרא Gemara
says, it's not a problem. מדרב נחמן Mid'Rav Nachman from what רב
נחמן Rav Nachman teaches. דאמר רב נחמן אמר היה רבי מאיר, D'amar
Rav Nachman amar haya Rabbi Meir, אפילו מצאו באשפה חתמו ונתנו לו
כשר, afilu matzo b'ashpah chasmo u'nosno lo kasher, that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says by a גט it could even be pre-written. Now we
don't rule that way, we have a לשמה requirement by a גט.
But the principle, forgetting לשמה, that it can be all written as
long as it's not signed, that's something that we hold by other
שטרות. shtaros. ואפילו רבנן לא פליגי עליה דרבי מאיר אלא בגיטי נשים
דבעינן לשמה כתיבה לשמה, V'afilu rabbanan lo pligi alei d'Rabbi Meir ela
b'gitei nashim d'ba'inan Lishmah k'sivah lishmah, they only argue by a גט,
but בשאר שטרות לא, b'sha'ar shtaros lo, by other שטרות shtaros you
can write the whole שטר... shtar... document and just, that wasn't in
the גמרא, Gemara and just
don't sign it and it's not a מחזי כשיקרא machzi k'shikra because
it doesn't mean anything until it's signed. So therefore you can write
an IOU and you can write a bill of sale and you
can write a כתובה. kesuvah. Think about what we do by the
כתובה. kesuvah, We have the name and we have the date and
we have the amount and we have everything in it right before
anything has happened. Okay, so you can do it, just don't sign
it yet and it's not a
מחזי
כשיקרא machzi k'shikra problem. Okay. אבל בשאר שטרות לא. aval b'shter shtaros
lo. דאמר רבי יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן: D'amar Rabbi Yitzchak amar Rabbi
Yochanan: שטר שלוה בו ופרעו. shtar she-lava bo u-perao. Let's say I
borrowed with a document that says I borrowed $1,000 from Charlie and
then I paid him off on the same day. אינו חוזר ולוה
בו. eino chozer ve-loveh bo. I can't reuse that שטר shtar today
to borrow money again. How come? I paid it and now I
want to reborrow, I don't know, but I can't reuse it even
on the same day שכבר נמחל שעבודו she-kvar nimchal shibudo because the
liens that were created by the document were already resolved by me
paying it off and part of what the document does is it
creates liens, so you cannot reuse it. Okay? Okay. It's like, you
know, trying to restrike a match. You can't reuse it once it's
been used. Okay. But the גמרא says טעמא דנמחל שעבודו. ta'ama de-nimchal
shibudo. The only reason it can't be, it can't be done is
because it's been already used, אבל משום שקרא לא חיישינן. aval mishum
shikra lo chaishinan. But just the fact that it had been already
written before you were ready to use it, that's not a problem.
So it's a bit, it's a more convoluted way of proving the
point but the basic point of the גמרא is that it's not
a problem to pre-write a document. So on the one hand we
rule like רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that you need לשמה and you
don't even write the boilerplate of a גט. On the other hand,
something that isn't a גט, you can completely write the whole thing
and there's no מחזי כשיקרא machzi k'shikra problem. Just don't sign it
until the time, which is why the irony, and I've mentioned this
before by the כתובה, kesuvah right? In a lot of the כתובות,
kesuvos, right? What they do is they write ורנינא מיניה, ve-ranina minei,
we did the קנין. kinyan. Okay? ורנינא מיניה, ve-ranina minei, we did
the קנין kinyan from the חתן. chosson. Okay? But it's supposed to
be וקנינא מיניה. ve-kanina minei. They don't want to write the word
that we did the קנין kinyan until the קנין kinyan is done.
The whole כתובה kesuvah is written. This word appears like this. You
do the, the חתן chosson does the קנין, kinyan, you fill this
in. Now we can say we've done the קנין kinyan and now
we sign it. Okay? So I never do that. I always just
write וקנינא מיניה ve-kanina minei because once or twice I forgot to
fill in the blank before, until after, until after they signed it.
And the bottom line is the reason we do it is it's
מחזי כשיקרא machzi k'shikra to say we did the קנין kinyan before
we did the קנין. kinyan. But you know what? The whole כתובה
kesuvah is מחזי כשיקרא machzi k'shikra because the whole כתובה says all
this stuff happened before it happened. So the bottom line is that
we're not concerned with מחזי כשיקרא. machzi k'shikra. You can write out
the text of a document as long as you don't sign it
and you can write it out ahead of time. But this is
like a מחזי כשיקרא חומרא machzi k'shikra chumra that people do and
that's, you know, and that's when they fill in the קוף kuf
after they see the קנין kinyan done. But to me it's just
asking for trouble so I don't do that. Okay. Yes Jar, what
you were, you were going to say something?
I was just going to ask what you do at that point.
Oh. Well you can fill it in afterwards because it's, because it's
clear from context that what it means. Like you know.
That last case with a long document and a loan that's paid
off and then you want the same loan from the same person
for the same amount. That's like a woman having two wives, that's
like a man having two wives with the same name and decides
to divorce
one and uses
the גט to divorce the other. Right, right, right. True.
We are scheduled to finish this מסכת maseches on שבת. Shabbos.
You're already looking to that, it's two months away? Yeah, six weeks.
You're already planning the סיום. siyum. Yeah, on what שבת? Shabbos?
March 12th. Okay.
So you should think about what you, it is a full, the
last דף daf. is a full, yeah, דף.
Oh you mean like whether we want to do like a קידוש
kiddush or something?
Yeah.